Eshwen Bhal

DATA SCIENTIST

22 Rownham Court, Rownham Mead, Bristol, United Kingdom. BS8 4YE

🛮 +44 (0) 78414 09961 | 💌 milanman.eshb@gmail.com | 🕥 eshwen | 🛅 eshwen-bhal-phd-714557195

Profile _____

I am a data scientist developing a web scraping pipeline for the Consumer Price Index alternative data sources transformation. I have recently completed a PhD in particle physics, searching for dark matter using big data from the Large Hadron Collider (LHC) at CERN. This involved statistical analysis of large datasets with expertise in Python, and solving wide ranging problems from physics standpoints to programming challenges. Additional responsibilities included providing detector-related expertise and software, teaching undergraduates, and public outreach. Aside from work, I partake in many activities such as taekwondo, weight lifting, hiking, and skiing.

Education _

University of Bristol

Bristol, United Kingdom

DOCTOR OF PHILOSOPHY IN PHYSICS

2016 - 2021

- Thesis: Searches for dark matter with a focus on invisibly decaying Higgs bosons using the full Run-2 dataset of the CMS experiment at the LHC *Under supervision of H. Flächer*
 - Explored various physics models in search of dark matter by analysing data from LHC's CMS experiment. Set **world leading limits** on the Higgs boson branching fraction to invisible states. **Leading estimated sensitivity** to GeV-scale dark matter.
 - Executed comprehensive statistical analysis on real and simulated data, meticulously documenting results and code.
 - Leveraging modern data science tools, vectorisation, and distributed computing to process multiple terabytes of data.
 - Author on papers in search of supersymmetry. Two papers in preparation in search of semi-visible jets and invisibly decaying Higgs bosons.
- Postgraduate student representative for particle physics, 2019–20 Role in Student-Staff Liaison Committee
- Long term attachment at world's largest particle physics laboratory **CERN** 18 month placement abroad in Switzerland
- Calorimeter Layer-2 on call expert and Level-1 Trigger shifter Additional responsibilities with CERN
 - Assisted in detector operations and monitoring so CMS experiment could take data efficiently and operate smoothly.
 - Developed and deployed software for subsystem of Level-1 Trigger to apply corrections and calibrations to data on the fly.

University of Exeter

Exeter, United Kingdom

MASTER OF PHYSICS WITH HONOURS IN PHYSICS WITH ASTROPHYSICS

2012 - 2016

- Grade: **First Class** 77 % overall mark (4.0 GPA equivalent)
- Dissertation: **Simulations of Exoplanet Light Curves** *Under supervision of T. Harries*
 - Developed software in C to simulate photons interacting simple planetary atmospheres, producing light curves akin to data from telescopes. Visualised model planets with maps of density and composition.
 - Able to model more complex atmospheres for comparison to real exoplanets to infer their composition.
 - Utilised Monte Carlo random sampling for scattering of photons, and parallelisation to efficiently run the code over millions of them.

Experience

Office for National Statistics

Newport, United Kingdom

DATA SCIENTIST 2021 – Present

- Web scraping products and prices from various retailers to assist in creating a more accurate Consumer Price Index.
- Building spiders in Python to reliably scrape websites with additional focus on unit testing, efficiency, and documentation.
- Maintaining and improving deployment on Google Cloud Platform for scheduled, automated execution.

University of Bristol

Bristol, United Kingdom

COMPUTATIONAL PHYSICS TUTOR

2019 - 2020

• Taught programming in Python to third year undergraduate students, with applications for numerically solving physics problems. Topics included linear algebra, differential equations, and Monte Carlo methods. Formally marked assignments and provided feedback.

Skills _

Data analysis

- Primary focus of my PhD concerns statistical analysis of large (multi-terabyte) datasets collected by the CMS experiment from the Large Hadron Collider.
- Developed analysis software for dark matter searches and detector-effect calibrations in Python and C++, using modern data science tools and parallel programming on computing grids.
- Visualisation with ROOT and matplotlib. Formal presentations of results with LaTeX and Microsoft PowerPoint.

Collaboration

• Belonging to, and working alongside, several groups of around a dozen people as well as a global research collaboration of over 4,000 people.

Problem solving

• Principal component of any physics degree. As an undergraduate, conducted more traditional pen-and-paper problem solving in many topics. As a PhD student, wrote robust, complex code to reliably solve physics problems numerically and perform data analysis in high energy particle physics.

Multitasking

• Often working on multiple projects at once with different people during PhD. These have included data analysis, software-implemented calibrations to data from detector effects, and expertise and shift work for subsystems of the detector.

Communication

- Presented formally in my PhD at all levels: regular working group updates, research group and collaboration-wide talks, and several conference posters and talks.
- Participated in outreach to the public at the CERN Open Days 2019 and at @Bristol.

Awards _____

2016	Dean's Commendation , in recognition of outstanding achievement in my fourth year	University of Exeter
2015	Physics Award , for being one of the three students with the highest marks in my third year	University of Exeter
2014	Dean's Commendation , in recognition of outstanding achievement in my second year	University of Exeter
2013	Physics Award , for being one of the three students with the highest marks in my first year	University of Exeter
2013	Dean's Commendation , in recognition of outstanding achievement in my first year	University of Exeter

Publications _____

2021	Searches for semi-visible jets in proton-proton collisions at \sqrt{s} = 13 TeV in hadronic final states	In preparation
2021	Search for an invisibly decaying Higgs boson in proton-proton collisions at \sqrt{s} = 13 TeV in final states with jets and missing transverse momentum	In preparation
2018	Search for natural and split supersymmetry in proton-proton collisions at \sqrt{s} = 13 TeV in final states with jets and missing transverse momentum	JHEP

Conference talks & posters _____

2019	CMS UK Conference, Searches for semi-visible jets in hadronic final states	Oxfordshire, UK
2019	University of Bristol PGR Conference , Search for dark matter via an invisibly decaying Higgs boson at CMS	Bristol, UK
2019	Institute of Physics HEPP and APP Conference , Combined search for an invisibly decaying Higgs boson in hadronic channels at 13 TeV with CMS	London, UK
2018	LHCP Conference , The CMS Level-1 jet and energy sum triggers in the LHC Run-II	Bologna, Italy
2017	University of Bristol PGR Conference, Dark matter searches at CMS at 13 TeV	Bristol, UK